So I tried to do a small good thing for my wife.
أشياء بسيطه وجيده حاولت القيام بها من اجل زوجتي
It makes me to stand here,
كانت سبب وقوفي هنا
the fame, the money I got out of it.
وسبب الشهره والمال الذي حققته من خلالها.
So what I did, I'd gone back to my early marriage days.
فما الذي قمت به، سوف اعود بالذاكره الى ايام زواجي الاولى.
What you did in the early marriage days,
مالذي عادة تعمله في باكورة ايام زواجك؟
you tried to impress your wife. I did the same.
انك حاولت اثارة اعجاب زوجتك ، لقد عملت الشئ نفسه.
On that occasion, I found my wife
في احدى المرات وجدت زوجتي
carrying something like this.
تحمل شيئا كهذا
I saw. "What is that?" I asked.
رأيته فقلت لها ماهذا؟
My wife replied, "None of your business."
اجابت زوجتي " ان هذا لايعنيك"
Then, being her husband, I ran behind her
وبسبب كوني زوجها اخذت اتبعها
and saw she had a nasty rag cloth.
ورأيت معها خرقه مقرفه
I don't even use that cloth to clean my two-wheeler.
لم اكن لاستخدم هذا القماش في تنظيف دراجتي.
Then I understood this -- adapting that unhygienic method
بعدها ادركت امرا -- انها تبنت أساليب غير صحيه
to manage her period days.
لتتدبر شئون فترة دورتها الشهريه
Then I immediately asked her, why are you [using] that unhygienic method?
سألتها مباشرة لماذا تستخدمين مثل هذه الطرق الغير صحيه
She replied, I also know about [sanitary pads],
أجابتني قائلة : انا اعلم بوجود الفوط الصحيه
but myself and my sisters, if they start using that,
ولكن بالنسبه لي ولااخواتي اذا بدأنا باستخدامها
we have to cut our family milk budget.
فسنضطر لخصمها من الميزانية المخصصه لحليب العائله
Then I was shocked. What is the connection between
بعدها صدمت، ماهو العلاقه بين
using a sanitary pad and a milk budget?
استخدام الفوط الصحية وميزانية الحليب
And it's called affordability.
وتسمى تدبير اقتصادي
I tried to impress my new wife by offering her a packet of sanitary pads.
حاولت اثارة اعجاب زوجتي الجديده بأن اقدم لها علبه من الفوط الصحيه
I went to a local shop, I tried to buy her a sanitary pad packet.
ذهبت الى محل قريب وحاولت ان اشتري علبة فوط صحيه
That fellow looks left and right,
صاحبها نظرات جهة اليمين والشمال
and spreads a newspaper, rolls it into the newspaper,
وبسط ورق جريده ولفها داخلها.
gives it to me like a banned item, something like that.
اعطاها لي كأنها ماده ممنوعه ، شي من هذا القبيل
I don't know why. I did not ask for a condom.
ولا اعلم السبب فأنا لم أطلب واقي ذكري.
Then I took that pad. I want to see that. What is inside it?
بعدها اخذت تلك الفوط ، اردت ان ارى ما بداخلها
The very first time, at the age of 29,
اول مره في سن ال 29
that day I am touching the sanitary pad, first ever.
اول مره في حياتي المس فوطه صحيه نسائيه.
I must know: How many of the guys here have touched a sanitary pad?
يجب ان اعرف كم هو عدد الرجال هنا سبق لهم لمس الفوط الصحيه
They are not going to touch that, because it's not your matter.
انهم لن يقربوها لأنها لا تعنيهم
Then I thought to myself, white substance, made of cotton --
بعدها فكرت وقلت لنفسي انها ماده بيضاء مصنوعه من القطن.
oh my God, that guy is just using a penny value of raw material --
يالهي هذا الرجل فقط يستخدم مايساوي قيمة البنس من المواد الخام
inside they are selling for pounds, dollars.
بينما في الداخل يبيعونها بالعديد من الجنيهات والدولارات.
Why not make a local sanitary pad for my new wife?
لماذا لا اعمل فوط صحية محلية لزوجتي الجديده.
That's how all this started, but after making a sanitary pad,
هكذا كانت البدايه ، ولكن بعد صنع الفوط الصحيه
where can I check it?
اين يمكن ان اختبرها
It's not like I can just check it in the lab.
انها ليست من ذلك النوع الذي يمكن فحصه في المختبرات
I need a woman volunteer. Where can I get one in India?
انني احتاج الى امرأه متطوعه، اين يمكن ان اجد واحده في الهند
Even in Bangalore you won't get [one], in India.
حتى في منطقة بانجلور في الهند انك لن تجد واحده.
So only problem: the only available victim is my wife.
لذا كانت المشكله ان الضحيه الوحيده المتاحه لي هي زوجتي
Then I made a sanitary pad and handed it to Shanti -- my wife's name is Shanti.
بعدها صنعت فوطه صحيه واعطيتها لـسانتي ..اسم زوجتي هو سانتي
"Close your eyes. Whatever I give,
" اغلقي عينيكي ، مهما كان ماسوف ترينه
it will be not a diamond pendant
فانه لن يكون قلادة الماس
not a diamond ring, even a chocolate,
ولا خاتم الماس ولاحتى قطعه من الشيكولاته
I will give you a surprise with a lot of tinsel paper rolled up with it.
سوف اقدم لكي مفاجأه ملفوفه بالكثير من الورق المبهرج
Close your eyes."
أغلقي عينيكي"
Because I tried to make it intimate.
لأني قصدت جعل الموقف حميمي
Because it's an arranged marriage, not a love marriage.
فزواجي مرتب له ان يكون وليس عن طريق علاقة حب.
(Laughter)
( ضحك)
So one day she said, openly, I'm not going to support this research.
في احد الايام قالت بصراحه انا لن ادعم هذا البحث
Then other victims, they got into my sisters.
وبالتالي الضحايا الاخريات كن شقيقاتي
But even sisters, wives, they're not ready to support in the research.
لكن حتى الشقيقات والزوجه غير مستعدين لدعم هذا البحث
That's why I am always jealous with the saints in India.
لذلك انا دائما أحسد القديسين في الهند
They are having a lot of women volunteers around them.
لأنهم محاطون بالكثير من المتطوعات
Why I am not getting [any]?
لماذا انا لا أحصل على متطوعات؟
You know, without them even calling, they'll get a lot of women volunteers.
انهم حتى لو لم يطلبوا سيحصلون على الكثير من المتطوعات
Then I used, tried to use the medical college girls.
بعدها حاولت استخدام متطوعات من كلية الطب.
They also refused. Finally, I decide,
ايضا هن رفضن ، وبالاخير قررت
use sanitary pad myself.
استخدام فوطه صحيه على نفسي
Now I am having a title like
ولي الان لقب يشبه لقب
the first man to set foot on the moon.
اول رجل تطأ قدماه القمر
Armstrong. Then Tenzing [and] Hillary, in Everest,
أرمسترونغ ...وتنزنج هيلاري المتسلق لقمة جبال افرست
like that Muruganantham is the first man
يشبههم ايضا "مورجانانثام " أول رجل
wore a sanitary pad across the globe.
لبس فوطه صحية في الكره الارضيه
I wore a sanitary pad. I filled animal blood in a football bottle,
لبست فوطه صحيه وعبأت دم حيوان داخل كرة قدم
I tied it up here, there is a tube going into my panties,
ربطتها هنا ، ويوجد انبوب يمر داخل بنطالي
while I'm walking, while I'm cycling, I made a press,
بينما امشي بينما اقود دراجتي ، اقوم بضغط
doses of blood will go there.
كميات من الدم تذهب هناك
That makes me bow down to any woman in front of me
هذا الشئ يجعلني انحني احتراما لأي امراه أمامي
to give full respect. That five days I'll never forget --
تلك الايام الخمسه التي لن انساها
the messy days, the lousy days, that wetness.
ايام فوضى وايام قذاره و ذلك البلل
My God, it's unbelievable.
يا الهي انه شي لا يصدق
But here the problem is, one company is making napkin
ولكن المشكله انه توجد شركه تعمل حفاظات
out of cotton. It is working well.
خاليه من مادة القطن ومع ذلك فهي تعمل جيدا
But I am also trying to make sanitary pad with the good cotton. It's not working.
بينما انا اعمل فوط صحيه بقطن جيد ومع ذلك لاتعمل
That makes me to want to refuse to continue this research and research and research.
هذا الامر جعلني اعزف عن مواصلة البحث ثم البحث ثم البحث
You need first funds.
تحتاج في المقام الاول الى تمويل
Not only financial crises, but because of the sanitary pad research,
لييست فقط من اجل الازمات الماليه ولكن من اجل الفوط الصحيه.
I come through all sorts of problems, including
مررت بكل انواع المشاكل من ضمنها
a divorce notice from my wife.
انذارات طلاق من زوجتي
Why is this? I used medical college girls.
لماذا يكون هذا؟ انا استخدم طالبات الكليه الطبيه
She suspects I am using as a trump card
لقد شكت باني اختلق ذريعه
to run behind medical college girls.
لملاحقة فتيات الكليه الطبيه
Finally, I came to know it is a special cellulose
في النهاية علمت انها من مادة خاصه من السليلوز
derived from a pinewood, but even after that,
تشتق من خشب الصنوبر، وحتى بعد ذلك
you need a multimillion-dollar plant like this
فانك تحتاج مصنع يكلف الملايين من الدولارات كهذا
to process that material. Again, a stop-up.
لتحويل هذه المادة... مره اخرى توقفت
Then I spend another four years to create my own
امضيت 4 سنوات لابتكار
machine tools, a simple machine tool like this.
معداتي الطبيه الخاصه ...معدات طبيه بسيطه كهذه.
In this machine, any rural woman can apply the same
بواسطة هذه الماكينه يمكن لاي امراه قروية التطبيق من نفس
raw materials that they are processing in the multinational plant,
المواد الخام المصنعه في مختلف مصانع البلدان
anyone can make a world-class napkin at your dining hall.
اي شخص يستطيع تصنيع حفاظات من طراز عالمي في صالة طعامه.
That is my invention.
هذا هو اختراعي
So after that, what I did,
بعد ذلك ماذا عملت
usually if anyone got a patent or an invention,
عادة اي شخص يملك براءة اختراع او اختراع
immediately you want to make, convert into this.
يرغب فورا بتصنيعه، يحوله الى هذا
I never did this. I dropped it just like this,
انا لم افعل ذلك ابدا، تجاهلته بكل سهوله
because you do this, if anyone runs after money,
لأنه اذا فعلت ذلك ...اي شخص يلهث وراء المال
their life will not [have] any beauty. It is boredom.
فان حياته تفقد رونقها، تصبح ممله
A lot of people making a lot of money, billion,
كثير من الناس جنو ثروه، مليارات
billions of dollars accumulating.
مليارات من الدولارات جمعوا
Why are they coming for, finally, for philanthropy?
لماذا بعد كل هذا يؤدون الصدقه
Why the need for accumulating money, then doing philanthropy?
لماذا يجمعون المال ثم ينفقونه بالتصدق
What if one decided to start philanthropy from the day one?
ماذا لو قرر شخص انتهاج الصدقه من اول يوم
That's why I am giving this machine
لهذا السبب انا ابذل هذه الماكينه
only in rural India, for rural women, because in India,
فقط في قرى الهند من اجل القرويات لأن في الهند
[you'll be] surprised, only two percent of women
سوف تتفاجأ فقط اثنان في المئه من النساء
are using sanitary pads. The rest, they're using a rag cloth,
يستخدمن الفوط الصحية اما الباقي فيستخدمن خرق باليه
a leaf, husk, [saw] dust, everything except sanitary pads.
الليف ، القشور ، نشارة الخشب ، الرماد ، اي شئ ما عدا الفوط الصحيه
It is the same in the 21st century. That's why I am going
وهذا يتزامن مع القرن الواحد والعشرين، هذا ما جعلني
to decide to give this machine only for poor women across India.
اقرر تقديم هذه الآله للنساء الفقيرات فقط في الهند
So far, 630 installations happened in 23 states
حتى الان تم تركيب 630 ماكينه في 23 ولايه
in six other countries.
في ستة بلدان
Now I'm on my seventh year sustaining against
تعتبر هذه السنه السابعه لي في مكابدة
multinational, transnational giants -- makes all MBA students a question mark.
المصانع العابره للحدود جعلت كل طلبة ماجستير ادارة الاعمال يتساءلون
A school dropout from Coimbatore, how he is able to sustaining?
كيف استطاع طالب لم ينهي تعليمه المدرسي في مدينة كايمباتور ان يكون بارعا؟
That makes me a visiting professor and guest lecturer in all IIMs.
جعل مني هذا بروفسور ومحاضر زائر في معهد IIMS
(Applause)
( تصفيق)
Play video one.
نشغل الفيديو الاول
(Video) Arunachalam Muruganantham: The thing I saw in my wife's hand, "Why are you using that nasty cloth?"
( الفيديو): الشي الذي رايته في يد زوجتي - لماذا تستخدمين هذه الخرقه الباليه
She replied immediately, "I know about napkins, but if I start
أجابتني فورا اعلم بشأن الحفاظات
using napkins, then we have to cut our family milk budget."
لكن اذا بدأت باستخدامها فسيكون على حساب ميزانية حليب الاسره
Why not make myself a low-cost napkin?
لماذا لا اصنع بنفسي حفاظات منخفضة التكاليف؟
So I decided I'm going to sell this new machine
لذا قررت بيع هذه الآله الجديده
only for Women Self Help Groups.
فقط لمجموعات نساء الخدمه الذاتيه
That is my idea.
هذه هي فكرتي
AM: And previously, you need a multimillion investment
في السابق كنت تحتاج استثمار بالملايين
for machine and all. Now, any rural woman can.
من اجل الماكينات والان المرأه القرويه تستطيع ذلك.
They are performing puja.
انهم يؤدون طقوس هنديه
(Video): (Singing)
( الفيديو) : (غناء)
You just think, competing giants,
مجرد التفكير بعمل منافسه ضد
even from Harvard, Oxford, is difficult.
جامعة هارفرد او اوكسفورد يعتبر صعب
I make a rural woman to compete with multinationals.
لقد جعلت المراه القرويه تنافس المنظمات الدوليه
I'm sustaining on seventh year.
انا اقف الان بعد سبع سنوات
Already 600 installations. What is my mission?
من تركيب 600 ماكينه، ماهي رسالتي؟
I'm going to make India
ساعمل على جعل الهند
[into] a 100-percent-sanitary-napkin-using country in my lifetime.
تحقق نسبة مئة في المئه في استخدام الفوط الصحيه
In this way I'm going to provide not less than a million
وبهذه الطريقه سأعمل على تزويد ليس اقل من مليون
rural employment that I'm going to create.
قروي بفرص العمل
That's why I'm not running after this bloody money.
لهذا السبب انا لا اجري خلف مال الدماء
I'm doing something serious.
انا افعل امر مهم
If you chase a girl, the girl won't like you.
اذا قمت بملاحقة فتاة فانها لن ترغب فيك
Do your job simply, the girl will chase you.
قم بوظيفتك ببساطه بعدها ببساطه البنت ستلاحقك
Like that, I never chased Mahalakshmi.
على هذا النحو، لا اطارد "مهلكشمي"
Mahalakshmi is chasing me, I am keeping in the back pocket.
مهلكشمي تطاردني ، انني احتفظ بالمال بجيبي الخلفي
Not in front pocket. I'm a back pocket man.
ليس في الجيب الامامي، انني رجل الجيب الخلفي
That's all. A school dropout saw your problem in the society
هذا كل مافي الامر، متخلف عن الدراسه رأى مشكله
of not using sanitary pad.
في عدم استخدام الفوط الصحيه
I am becoming a solution provider. I'm very happy.
انا الان اصبحت حلال مشاكل انا جدا سعيد
I don't want to make this as a corporate entity.
لا اريد ان اجعل من هذا شركة ربحية
I want to make this as a local sanitary pad movement
انا فقط اريد جعل هذا حركة محليه للفوط الصحية
across the globe. That's why I put all the details
في كل العالم. هذا هو سبب وضعي لجميع التفاصيل
on public domain like an open software.
في موقع الكتروني كبرنامج كمبيوتر مفتوح المصدر.
Now 110 countries are accessing it. Okay?
الان 110 دوله دخلوا الموقع ، جيد؟
So I classify the people into three:
لذا قسمت الناس الى ثلاث:
uneducated, little educated, surplus educated.
غير متعلمين ، متعلمين قليلا ، متعلمين زياده عن اللازم.
Little educated, done this. Surplus educated,
شخص متعلم قليلا فعل كل هذا. ايها المتعلمون زياده عن اللازم
what are you going to do for the society?
مالذي ستعملونه للمجتمع؟
Thank you very much. Bye!
شكرا جزيلا لكم ، مع السلامه
(Applause)
( تصفيق)